<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ImplementationGuide
    xmlns="http://hl7.org/fhir">
    <id value="hl7.fhir.us.odh"/>
    <meta>
        <versionId value="268"/>
        <lastUpdated value="2023-02-08T17:16:13.099+00:00"/>
        <source value="#9jw0zdPqWHmvtSCR"/>
    </meta>
    <url value="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/odh/ImplementationGuide/hl7.fhir.us.odh"/>
    <version value="1.3.0"/>
    <name value="HL7_FHIR_Profile_Occupational_Data_for_Health_ODH_Release_1_3_Standard_for_Trial_Use"/>
    <title value="HL7 FHIR Profile: Occupational Data for Health (ODH), Release 1, STU 1.3 (Standard for Trial Use)"/>
    <status value="draft"/>
    <date value="2022-10-06T00:00:00.000Z"/>
    <publisher value="HL7 International Public Health Work Group"/>
    <contact>
        <name value="HL7 International - Public Health"/>
        <telecom>
            <system value="url"/>
            <value value="http://www.hl7.org/Special/committees/pher"/>
        </telecom>
    </contact>
    <description value="**HL7 FHIR Profile: Occupational Data for Health (ODH), Release 1.3 (Standard for Trial Use)**&#xA;&#xA;This Implementation Guide is a reconciled version, containing changes in response to comments received in the Sept. 2018 ballot. It has been updated to FHIR R4.0.1.&#xA;&#xA;**Introduction and Guidance**&#xA;&#xA;This Implementation Guide (IG) contains profiles to implement support for Occupational Data for Health (ODH). ODH describes structured work information primarily designed to facilitate clinical care, including population health and value-based care. ODH also can be used to support public health reporting. ODH is not designed to support billing activities. &#xA;This set of FHIR profiles is specified as a composition resource, but it is not intended to be used as a stand-alone composition. Rather, the desired content should be included in broader IGs and available as a response to requests for ODH information. Some use cases may leverage only a subset of the ODH profiles, and these should be specified within those work products. For instance, in the Vital Records Death Reporting (VRDR) IG, the data requirements for work information are limited to  those in the Usual Work profile.&#xA;While this profile is specified for the US Realm, the design is intended to also support international needs. Three of the referenced value sets—Occupation, Industry, and Supervisory Level— are necessarily US specific. The remaining three value sets—Work Schedule, Employment Status, and Work Classification—use international concepts. Input is requested regarding whether these should be specified as ‘extensible’, ‘required’ (using ‘text only’ where a concept does not yet exist such as a new occupation), or as an ‘example’ for those US specific concepts.&#xA;&#xA;**Background**&#xA;&#xA;The majority of adults in the U.S. spend more than half their waking hours at work. Therefore, health and work are inextricably inter-related. For example, the management of chronic conditions requires taking the patient’s work environment into consideration. Work-related conditions are often first brought to the attention of a primary care provider. Some conditions related to exposure to hazards in the workplace can have a long latency, requiring knowledge of a person’s work history for recognition, diagnosis, and treatment. The recognition of new conditions related to previously unknown workplace hazards has often come from astute clinicians, which requires knowledge of the patient’s work. ONC has indicated recognition of the value of work information for health care.&#xA;The incorporation of ODH into Electronic Health Records (EHRs) and other health IT systems presents an opportunity to improve health in relation to work. ODH provides a structure and standardization for work information that can be used across systems to take advantage of system tools for clinical decision support, population health, and public health. Research has been conducted and guidance is available to support clinicians, and the use of ODH by health IT systems can support identification of patients that would benefit the most from this knowledge.&#xA;&#xA;**Scope**&#xA;&#xA;The Occupational Data for Health (ODH) FHIR IG covers information about a patient’s work, including some voluntary work, or a patient’s household members’ work. ODH is designed for the social history section of a medical record, to facilitate clinical care in multiple disciplines and delivery environments. ODH can be used for clinical decision support, population health activities and value-based care, and public health reporting. The scope of the work information in ODH includes:&#xA;&#xA;•	Employment Status&#xA;&#xA;•	Retirement Date&#xA;&#xA;•	Combat Zone Period&#xA;&#xA;•	Past or Present Job for the patient or a household member, which includes:&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Past or Present Job Occupation&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Past or Present Job Industry&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Work Classification&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Work Schedule, which includes:&#xA;				&#xA;				- Weekly Work Days&#xA;				&#xA;				- Daily Work Hours&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Job Duty&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Occupational Hazard&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Employer name&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Employer address&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Related Subject (when it is Past or Present Job of a household member of the person)&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Start/End Dates&#xA;&#xA;•	Usual Work of the patient or a household member, which includes:&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Usual Occupation&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Usual Industry&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Usual Occupation Duration&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Related Subject (when it is Usual Work of a household member of the person)&#xA;		&#xA;		o	Start Date&#xA;&#xA;**Known Issues and Limitations**&#xA;&#xA;This IG includes more extensive occupational data than typically collected in current systems. The content and structure of this IG is intended to inform clinical care, support population health, and contribute to public health activities. While there may be some overlap with administrative and billing information maintained by some systems, the information in this IG is not designed to support billing and administrative needs.&#xA;While multiple retirement dates are supported, the retirement date is not linked to any specific job, or usual occupation.&#xA;&#xA;**Credits**&#xA;&#xA;Co-Editor:&#xA;Lori Reed-Fourquet&#xA;e-HealthSign, LLC&#xA;lfourquet@ehealthsign.com&#xA;&#xA;Co-Editor:&#xA;Rob Hausam&#xA;Hausam Consulting&#xA;rob@hausamconsulting.com&#xA;&#xA;Co-Editor:&#xA;Mark Kramer&#xA;MITRE Corporation&#xA;mkramer@mitre.org&#xA;&#xA;This set of FHIR profiles was produced and developed through the efforts of a project of the National Institute of Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH), the U.S. federal agency responsible for conducting research and making recommendations for the prevention of work-related injury and illness. NIOSH is a part of the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). NIOSH consulted stakeholders in clinical care, public health, health IT, health informatics and  U.S. government agencies to develop ODH. The HL7® Public Health and Emergency Response Work Group sponsored development of this set of FHIR profiles. Co-sponsoring HL7® Work Groups were Orders and Observations (OO), Patient Administration (PA), and Clinical Quality Initiative (CQI).&#xA;The following individuals provided subject matter expertise for this set of FHIR profiles: Genevieve Barkocy Luensman, NIOSH; Eileen Storey, Professional Services Partners, formerly NIOSH; Margaret S. Filios, NIOSH; Christina Socias-Morales, NIOSH; Lauren Brewer, NIOSH; Barbara Wallace, Professional Services Partners.&#xA;&#xA;**Authors**&#xA;&#xA;Name	Email/URL&#xA;HL7 International - Public Health	http://www.hl7.org/Special/committees/pher"/>
    <jurisdiction>
        <coding>
            <system value="urn:iso:std:iso:3166"/>
            <code value="US"/>
            <display value="United States of America"/>
        </coding>
        <text value="United States of America"/>
    </jurisdiction>
    <copyright value="©2020+ HL7 International Public Health Work Group. Package hl7.fhir.us.odh#1.0.0 based on FHIR 4.0.1. Generated 2020-01-08.&#xA;Links: Home | QA Report | Search | Version History external | CC0 external | Propose a change external"/>
    <packageId value="hl7.fhir.us.odh"/>
    <fhirVersion value="4.0.1"/>
    <dependsOn id="hl7fhiruscore">
        <uri value="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/core/ImplementationGuide/hl7.fhir.us.core"/>
        <packageId value="hl7.fhir.us.core"/>
        <version value="5.0.1"/>
    </dependsOn>
    <dependsOn id="uscdcphinvads">
        <uri value="http://fhir.org/packages/us.cdc.phinvads/ImplementationGuide/us.cdc.phinvads"/>
        <packageId value="us.cdc.phinvads"/>
        <version value="0.12.0"/>
    </dependsOn>
    <definition>
        <grouping id="primary-profiles">
            <name value="Primary Profiles"/>
        </grouping>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="StructureDefinition/odh-CombatZonePeriod"/>
                <display value="Combat Zone Period"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="Combat Zone Period"/>
            <description value="A Combat Zone Period Observation is a clinical statement indicating the self-reported date range(s)when a person worked in what is considered a combat zone. Both civilian workers, such as Department of Defense contractors, and military service members could have worked in combat zones. Many people who have served in the military seek care first outside of the Veterans Health Administration system. Collecting this observation can facilitate important conversations about possible related health concerns, potentially prompting referral to the Department of Veterans’ Affairs (VA)."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <groupingId value="primary-profiles"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="StructureDefinition/odh-Employer-extension"/>
                <display value="Employer"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="Employer"/>
            <description value="A person or organization that hires the services of another. This contains the address of the employer, which might not be the work location."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="StructureDefinition/odh-EmploymentStatus"/>
                <display value="Employment Status"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="Employment Status"/>
            <description value="The self-reported current and/or historical status about a person’s economic relationship to work (e.g. having one or more jobs), including start and end dates. A person’s Employment Status could change over time, for example, a person could be employed following a period of choosing to not be in the labor force. Outside of ODH, the employment arrangement between an employer and a person (one job) has sometimes been referred to as a person’s ‘employment status.’ However, in ODH, Employment Status is used to characterize a person, Work Classification is used to characterize a job, and Retirement Date is used to characterize a person as retired."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <groupingId value="primary-profiles"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="StructureDefinition/odh-OccupationalDataForHealth"/>
                <display value="Occupational Data For Health"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="Occupational Data For Health"/>
            <description value="covers information about a patient’s work, including some voluntary work, or a patient’s household members’ work. ODH is designed for the social history section of a medical record, to facilitate clinical care in multiple disciplines and delivery environments. ODH can be used for clinical decision support, population health activities and value-based care, and public health reporting."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <groupingId value="primary-profiles"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="StructureDefinition/odh-PastOrPresentJob"/>
                <display value="Past Or Present Job"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="Past Or Present Job"/>
            <description value="A Past or Present Occupation Observation is a clinical statement about the type of work done by a person in a job, as reported by that person. It includes a set of self-reported, related observations that remain associated with one-another to characterize the job and provide clinically-relevant information. It also can be used in a minor’s record for the job(s) of people who share a home with the person (see optional related subject). A job is defined as a work situation, training position, or (potentially clinically-relevant) volunteer position held for a specified time period; for a given job, updates to Job Occupation, Past or Present Industry (Job Industry), Supervisory Level, or Employer would constitute a new job or volunteer position. A person can have more than one job at the same time and multiple jobs over time. Knowledge about a person’s job(s) informs diagnosis and management of illness and injury; it also informs management of health in the work environment, regardless of whether a condition is work-related. While knowing about a person’s current job(s) is likely to be most important, some work-related health conditions can manifest after a long latency so a history of jobs can also provide valuable information. This set of related Job observations also can provide information for public health to locate infectious disease outbreaks and intervene to prevent further illness. Public health can also use these data to analyze work-related conditions such as silicosis, pesticide poisoning, and some types of cancer to identify Occupations, Industry sectors and Employers for whom interventions are needed to mitigate risk."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <groupingId value="primary-profiles"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="StructureDefinition/odh-RetirementDate"/>
                <display value="Retirement Date"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="Retirement Date"/>
            <description value="A Date of Retirement Observation is a clinical statement about a self-reported date (at least year) that a person considers themselves to have ‘retired’. If present, the person has retired. A person can be both retired and employed; most often, a person would be retired from one job and employed in another job."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <groupingId value="primary-profiles"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="StructureDefinition/odh-UsualWork"/>
                <display value="Usual Work"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="Usual Work"/>
            <description value="A Usual Occupation Observation is a clinical statement about the type of work (paid or unpaid) done by a person for the longest amount of time during his or her life, not including voluntary work. It includes a set of self-reported, related components about the work a person performed for the longest amount of time during his or her life, regardless of the person’s current job and regardless of whether or not the person performed this work for a continuous time. It also can be used in a minor’s record for the Usual Work of people who share a home with the person (see optional related subject). Usual Work supports recognition of new and known chronic conditions which evolve over many years and may become evident after the person is no longer performing that type of work, e.g., some respiratory conditions and cancers. These data also are used by public health entities and medical researchers to investigate the relationship between conditions and exposures at work and illnesses, causes of death, or cancer."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <groupingId value="primary-profiles"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="ValueSet/obf-datatype-YesNoVS"/>
                <display value="Yes No VS"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="Yes No VS"/>
            <description value="Value set indicating yes or no (values drawn from Snomed CT), equivalent to LL361-7."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="StructureDefinition/odh-isCurrentJob-extension"/>
                <display value="ODHIsCurrentJob-extension"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="ODHIsCurrentJob-extension"/>
            <description value="A flag indicating if this is the person's current job (at the time the resource was last updated)"/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="Observation/observation-odh-combat-zone-period-sample"/></reference>
            <name value="Combat Zone Period Example"/>
            <description value="This example includes a combat zone period of 1 year for patient Maya Gordon."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <exampleCanonical value="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/odh/StructureDefinition/odh-CombatZonePeriod"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="Observation/observation-odh-employment-status-sample"/></reference>
            <name value="Employment Status Example"/>
            <description value="This example shows an employment status of 'Employed' for patient Maya Gordon."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <exampleCanonical value="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/odh/StructureDefinition/odh-EmploymentStatus"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="Observation/observation-odh-retirement-date-sample"/></reference>
            <name value="Retirement Date Example"/>
            <description value="This example shows a retirement date for test patient Maya Gordon."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <exampleCanonical value="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/odh/StructureDefinition/odh-RetirementDate"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="Patient/patient-odh-maya-gordon"/></reference>
            <name value="ODH Patient Maya Gordon"/>
            <description value="This is an example of patient, Maya Gordon, that is associated with the work profile examples."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="true"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="Observation/observation-odh-usual-work-sample"/></reference>
            <name value="Usual Work Example"/>
            <description value="Example for the Usual Work profile"/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <exampleCanonical value="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/odh/StructureDefinition/odh-UsualWork"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="Composition/composition-odh-occupational-data-for-health-sample"/>
                <display value="Occupational Data Composition for Maya Gordon"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="Occupational Data Composition for Maya Gordon"/>
            <description value="Complete composition example of work information for patient Maya Gordon."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <exampleCanonical value="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/odh/StructureDefinition/odh-OccupationalDataForHealth"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="Organization/organization-odh-south-hospital"/>
                <display value="South Hospital"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="South Hospital"/>
            <description value="US Core Organization - South Hospital Example"/>
            <exampleBoolean value="true"/>
        </resource>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="Observation/observation-odh-past-or-present-job-sample"/></reference>
            <name value="Past or Present Job Example"/>
            <description value="This is an example of a Past or Present Job for patient, Maya Gordon. This example includes coded Occupation, Industry, Work Classification (compensation sector and employment type), Work Schedule, Weekly Work Days, Daily Work Hours, Job Duties, and Occupational Hazard."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
            <exampleCanonical value="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/odh/StructureDefinition/odh-PastOrPresentJob"/>
        </resource>
        <page>
            <nameUrl value="index.html"/>
            <title value="Home Page"/>
            <generation value="markdown"/>
            <page>
                <nameUrl value="downloads.html"/>
                <title value="Downloads"/>
                <generation value="markdown"/>
            </page>
        </page>
        <parameter>
            <code value="jira-code"/>
            <value value="ohd"/>
        </parameter>
        <parameter>
            <code value="defaultVersion"/>
            <value value="1.3.0"/>
        </parameter>
        <parameter>
            <code value="releaselabel"/>
            <value value="STU 1.3"/>
        </parameter>
        <parameter>
            <code value="copyrightyear"/>
            <value value="2020+"/>
        </parameter>
    </definition>
</ImplementationGuide>